Hello English learners. Welcome
back to English Pod. My name is Marko.
And my name is Catherine.
So what are we talking about today, Marko?
Well, we're talking about one of my
favorite topics which are computers.
Yes, you're a little bit of a nerd.
A little bit.
I love computers and technology
and everything that's related to it.
So that's what we're going to be looking at
today. Maybe we're buying a new computer.
Well, I anticipate learning
something from this
because there are a lot
of those fancy big words
that I don't know that have to
do with processors and gigos.
So that's going to be
coming up in a minute here.
But first, let's just jump right in
and take a listen to today's dialogue.
So can you fix it?
I'm sorry, sir.
This computer is not broken or damaged.
It's simply just too old.
That's why your programs and
applications are running slow.
There really isn't much I can do.
What do you mean?
I bought this computer
just three years ago.
Yes, but technology
is ever changing and
technology is becoming
obsolete faster and faster.
Okay. I know where this is going.
How much will it cost me
to get a new computer?
Well, this desktop over
here is our latest model.
It has a four gigahertz
processor with 16
gigabytes in RAM and a
hard disk with one terabyte.
Of course, it includes a mouse,
keyboard, and desk speakers.
I have no idea what you were talking about.
I just want to know if it's good.
And if I'll be able to
play solitaire without
the computer crashing
or freezing all the time.
This PC is top of the line and
I guarantee it will never freeze.
If it does, we'll give you your money back.
All right, we're back.
I think it's a very typical case.
It's something fixed and they say,
"We can't fix it. You need a new one.
" Yes, and not only a new one, but
a bigger and better and faster one.
And more expensive obviously.
Obviously, it's called the upsell.
The upsell, yeah.
All right, so there were some
very difficult words I think
because they're very specific
related to technology and computers.
So why don't we look at those
now in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
All right, so the first word we have today
is when something is no longer in use.
Okay, so this word is obsolete.
It's obsolete.
Absolutely, and we're
not just talking about like,
"Oh, I haven't touched
that pen in like ten years.
" We're talking about a piece
of technology that is no longer
useful because there's something
else that can do a better job.
Right, and actually not
only with technology,
we also have words
that are obsolete, right?
Exactly, like thigh or thigh.
You or yours.
Classical English.
We don't use thigh anymore.
No, but...
Thou art very summary today in Marco.
We don't use that anymore.
That's obsolete English, right?
Absolutely, words.
Exactly, so obsolete
means it's no longer of use.
We have better and
newer things in its place.
All right, and now moving
on when the salesman was
describing the characteristics
of the computer,
he used some prefixes that
were a little bit strange, right?
Like, for example, "giga.
" "giga" was?
"giga."
All right, so these are actually
prefixes that have to do with numbers.
And so this is not just a computer thing.
This is a math thing or science thing.
So, okay, so we've got three
different prefixes, a prefix
is something we attack on
at the beginning of a word.
So, we have Hertz or Bite, right?
These are little bits of a computer, Bite.
Right, so you have like megabytes.
Megabytes, we've all heard before.
That's smallest here.
We've got megabytes, but bigger
than megabyte, we've got gigabytes.
A gigabyte.
So now, for example, the
hard drives are 250 gigabytes.
You might even hear someone say gigs.
It's got a 250 gig hard drive.
Yeah.
But what's bigger than gigabyte?
Now it's the terabyte.
Oh, tera, it sounds like bone bone bone.
Yeah, I actually wondered what
would happen after gigabyte.
Because it's so much information
already and now it's the terabyte.
So it's like 1,000 gigabytes.
So that's like 200 movies.
That's probably more than that.
It's amazing the amount
of storage you can have.
And how small it actually is.
So, mega giga tera going
from littleest to biggest.
All right.
And well, he described
four giga Hertz processor.
Okay, so the processor is our next word.
And this is actually
something that determines
how fast your
computer is going to run.
So it comes from the
word to process, right?
Right.
To like calculate or
to think do even to do.
So you have different
examples, like a word processor.
Right.
So that's like Microsoft Word.
It allows you to make Word documents.
You can also say to process that up.
You're trying to calculate it.
But in this case, a
processor is like a little brain.
That's the center of the computer.
And that's where all the
information gets processed.
Yeah.
So it's the brain of the
computer essentially.
And the bigger it is, the faster it can go.
Exactly.
And well, if you don't have a very good
processor, your computer is bound to freeze.
Okay.
So freezing is another key word.
Especially when talking about computers.
This one drives me nuts.
To freeze, it means to stop moving.
Right.
So well, it has a couple
of different meanings.
You might have heard it about ice before.
But to freeze, here we're
talking about stopping moving.
So we have a game called freeze tag.
Or if I touch you, you
have to stop running.
Right.
But here we're talking
about a computer freezing.
I'm moving my mouse and I'm typing.
And all of a sudden my mouse doesn't move.
I can't close or open or do anything.
And it's really frustrating.
Especially if you're doing something
and you didn't save your work.
It's not.
Right.
So if your computer freezes,
then usually you have to
restart it or turn it off or not.
So that is about it for those words.
But let's take another
listen and slow the dialogue
down this time so you can
catch some of those big words.
So can you fix it?
I'm sorry, sir.
This computer is not broken or damaged.
It's simply just too old.
That's why your programs and
applications are running slow.
There really isn't much I can do.
What do you mean?
About this computer just three years ago.
Yes, but technology is ever changing
and technology is becoming
obsolete faster and faster.
Okay, I know where this is going.
How much will it cost me
to get a new computer?
Well, this desktop over
here is our latest model.
It has a four gigahertz
processor with 16
gigabytes in RAM and a
hard disk with one terabyte.
Of course, it includes a mouse,
keyboard and desk speakers.
I have no idea what you were talking about.
I just want to know if it's good
and if I'll be able to play solitaire
without the computer
crashing or freezing all the time.
This PC is top of the
line and I guarantee it will
never freeze if it does, we'll
give you your money back.
Great, so we are back.
So now let's jump into
today's fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
All right, so on fluency builder,
we're going to take a look
at three different phrases.
For example, the salesman
was describing technology
and said that it's ever changing.
Okay, so this is a sort
of poetic line here.
So ever changing means always changing.
Always, always changing.
And so we can say that
the ocean is ever changing.
You know, the waves are always changing.
But in this case, he's saying that
technology is always changing.
It's always progressing into something new.
And so that is a key
selling point for this guy.
Right, so this is actually
a very interesting word.
We can use it like in your
example, beyond technology,
like the way like the
sea is ever changing.
So why don't we listen to
a couple of other examples?
Example one.
There's always something
new in this ever changing world.
Example two.
Times are ever changing and we
must prepare ourselves better every day.
Example three.
The flu is an ever changing virus
that continues to claim many lives.
All right, we're back.
So now we understand ever changing.
So the man who's trying to buy this
computer, or at least get his computer fixed,
really starts to get
frustrated with the salesman.
And he says, "Okay, I
know where this is going.
" So he hears the sales pitch.
He hears this guy trying
to loosen him up a little bit.
He says, "I know
where this is going.
" What does this mean?
Where something is going?
So basically what direction, a conversation,
or a topic, or a situation is taking?
Okay, so he's saying, "I know
why you're telling me these things.
" Right.
I know you're motive.
All right, know what's happening.
I know what you're going to say.
Okay, so he's essentially
saying, "I know
you're going to try
and sell me a computer.
" Right.
So you can use it in other circumstances.
Right, for example, a relationship.
I don't know where this is going.
Right, what is going?
Classic break-up line.
I just don't think I know
where this is going anymore.
So in reference to the relationship, right?
Yes.
We don't know what's happening.
Are we serious, or are we
maybe going to get married?
I don't know anymore.
I can't tell where this movie is going.
It's so like, ooh, here
and there and boring.
I don't know the plot.
Yeah.
All right.
So it's a very common phrase.
It sounds very natural
when you say it right.
It does.
And that's why it's influencing people.
It really helps you
sound like a more native
English speaker when you
use these kind of phrases.
And the next one is also very, very good.
When he describes the condition of
the computer, he says it's top of the line.
Top of the line.
Now, what line we're talking about?
I do not know.
But this is above average line.
Right.
So this is the best of the best.
This is the top model or the top computer.
And you can definitely imagine
a car salesman using this.
Yeah.
Yes.
This BMW is top line.
The best money can buy.
That's another good one.
So basically, top of the
line is the best of the best,
the above average.
More than above average.
It's really, it's the best you can do.
And so the guy's saying,
listen, this is our best computer.
Really, you should buy it.
And obviously, top of the
line is like, that's a lot of money.
Yeah.
It's usually for something that
costs money right for things.
You wouldn't really
use it for a person, right?
He's top of the line.
No, no, no, no.
Top of the line, I think, generally, refers
to electronics and cars or motorcycles.
And so you often hear
top line stereo, top line TV.
Top of the line car.
But you wouldn't say this
about food or people or art.
Yeah, you wouldn't say this
painting is top of the line.
Not about very unique things.
You would say this about
kind of manufactured things.
Very good.
So we've taken a look
at a lot of great phrases.
Why don't we listen to our
dialogue for the last time?
And then we'll come back.
So can you fix it?
I'm sorry, sir.
This computer is not broken or damaged.
It's simply just too old.
That's why your programs and
applications are running slow.
There really isn't much I can do.
What do you mean?
I bought this computer
just three years ago.
Yes, but technology is ever changing,
and technology is becoming
obsolete faster and faster.
Okay.
I know where this is going.
How much will it cost me
to get a new computer?
Well, this desktop over
here is our latest model.
It has a four gigahertz
processor with 16
gigabytes in RAM and a
hard disk with one terabyte.
Of course, it includes a mouse,
keyboard, and desk speakers.
I have no idea what you were talking about.
I just want to know if it's good.
And if I'll be able to
play solitaire without
the computer crashing
or freezing all the time.
This PC is top of the line, and
I guarantee it will never freeze.
If it does, we'll give you your money back.
All right, we're back, so computers.
Catherine, I know you
recently got a nice Macintosh.
Yeah, yeah, I did.
It's one of those big screen ones, right?
Yeah, it is. It's a desktop.
Right, so it's not a laptop.
And it's got a very fast processor
because Macs started using Intel processors
a couple of years ago, and
that made them much faster.
Wow, and it has this processor
actually has two cores, right?
So basically, it has two different
brains, almost within one processor.
Which gives it really bad headaches.
She complains to me often.
Are you a big Mac fan or PC fan?
I'm a Mac fan, but I've been converted.
My roommate in college, my
sophomore year, had a Mac, and
ever since then, I've really
gotten into them, so really.
I went Mac and didn't turn back.
I still honestly cannot really use a Mac.
I get confused.
I'm looking for the start button, and
I'm looking for where my documents are.
It's really hard to change over, right?
But once you do, you
don't want to change back
because everything is so much easier on
a Mac, but if you're really into PC gaming,
then you should probably
stick with it, stick with the PCs
because the games just
don't really compare on Macs.
But I've heard that also Macs
don't really suffer from viruses, right?
No, they don't, which is
great, because I always used
to get these viruses that
will float on my computer
because, you know, you opened
some email and all that stuff.
There's nastiness on your desktop.
Well, now I don't really have that problem.
And also, there's
really wonderful photo
editing software and
video editing software.
So everything's just really
easy to find and easy to use.
What about you listeners?
Do you prefer the Mac?
Do you prefer the PC or maybe some of our
listeners don't really even like computers?
Well, let us know either way, we're
very curious to hear what you have to say.
And, of course, writing on our comment
section is great practice for your English.
Right, so we'll see you guys
there, and until next time.
Bye, everyone. Bye.